Guide to the John Ruskin Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Manuscripts, 1826-1897; Series II
  - Unbound Manuscripts
    - Dilecta - Autograph manuscript fragment, together with autograph manuscript fragment of Praeterita., undated (Box 31)
      Accompanied by galley and page proofs of Chapter VIII, "The State of Denmark", inscribed and dated in Ruskin's hand, "First proof for my G. D. [God-daughter, Constance Oldham], 12 Nov. [18]86".
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1959
    - Early Poems Ia - Autograph manuscript., 1827-1842 (Box 31)
      Accompanied by a manuscript title page and list of contents by Alexander H. Wedderburn.
      The edges of the pages are charred, affecting the text in some places.
      Gift of Charles E. Goodspeed, 1942 and 1943
    - The Exile of St. Helena - Manuscript copy, in an unidentified hand, of part of the poem., [1838?] (Box 31)
    - Fors Clavigera - Autograph manuscript of a portion of the text. Oxford., 1897 July 18 (Box 31)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Frank Altschul Fund
    - Fors Clavigera - Autograph manuscript of portions of the text., undated; 2 (Box 31)
      The following are included: portions of letters 12, 13, 20, 58 (with first draft of St. George's creed), 60, 61, 62 (with the corrected proof), 63, 64, 74, 81, 82, 84 (complete), 87, 88, 92 (complete except for quotations at the end from Scott), 95. Appendices 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 12, 15, 16, 18, 19, 20, 21, 24, 26.
      Also included is part of Ruskin's report for the St. George's Guild, 1879, and six additional sheets, printed in the Library edition, volume 30, pp. 15-19, 153-155.
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. by C. B. Tinker, 1930 November
    - Hereford, 16 March 84 - Autograph manuscript of a piece from an autobiographical text, 1884 March 16 (Box 31)
      This manuscript looks like a draft of a letter, but is actually a piece from one of Ruskin's autobiographical works.
    - "I find much more difficulty..." - Autograph manuscript note, [1890] (Box 31)
    - A Joy Forever - Autograph manuscript of the revised preface, signed., 1880 April 29 (Box 31)
      Accompanied by proof sheets of pp. 199-202 and 209-216 with notes and manuscript corrections in Ruskin's hand.
      Gift of Ward E. Terry, 1936
    - Laws of Fesole - Autograph manuscript of a large portion of the text., [1877-1879] (Box 31)
      Accompanied by diagrams in pencil and ink, corrected proof sheets, and two drawings: "Carnation," in full shade (wash), and "Herb Robert" (pencil).
      Edges of the pages are charred, affecting the text.
    - Love's Meinie - Autograph manuscript of a draft of the preface., 1881 June 9-16 (Box 31)
      Includes photocopy of the entry from the auction catalogue.
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund
    - Map of Scandinavia - Autograph manuscript map drawn by Ruskin, 1830 September 18 (Box 31)
    - Mathematical problem - autograph manuscript, likely by Ruskin., undated (Box 31)
      Edges charred, affecting text.
    - The Monastery - Manuscript, in an unidentified hand, of passages in verse., undated (Box 31)
      Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Charles E. Goodspeed to Prof. Chauncey B. Tinker regarding the manuscript. 1942 November 4.
    - The Peace Song - Autograph manuscript of a poem in five stanzas., undated (Box 31)
      Mounted on a stub. Edges charred, affecting text.
    - Poetical Journal of a Continental Tour - Autograph manuscript in verse., [1835] (Box 31)
    - Praeterita - Autograph manuscript notes, corrected, for chapter XI., undated (Box 31)
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Joan R. Severn to Lady Nottage. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. 1889 November 15.
    - Queen of the Air: Being a Study of the Greek Myths of Clouds and Storm - Two manuscript fragments, corrected., undated (Box 31)
      Bought from C. R. Johnson on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund
    - Receipts (2), in manuscript, signed, for money obtained from Smith, Elder & Co. for editions of The Crown of Wild Olives and Ethics of the Dust, 1866 January 3, 1866 August 15 (Box 31)
      Bought on the Childs Fund, 1961
    - Roadside Songs of Tuscany - Manuscript fragments and corrected page proofs., undated (Box 31)
      The following are included: 1. Editor's preface, manuscript. 2. Introductory: The Story of Lucia, manuscript. 3. The Story of Faustina, page proof with additions. 4. Editor's note on the drawing of the Samaritan, page proof with corrections. 5. Editor's preface to the Song of the Shepherds, page proof with corrections.
      Bought from E. Seligmann on the Plain Fund, 1954 June 30
    - Testimonials - 2 autograph manuscript signed testimonials written on behalf of Miss Ellen Burrows. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1880 December 10, 1883 December 27 (Box 31)
      Includes an envelope addressed to Mrs. Cousins.
    - To Poesie - Manuscript in an unidentified hand., undated (Box 31)
    - "Write an article..." - Autograph manuscript of 2 lines, 1884 July 4 (Box 31)
      Given by the Yale Library Associates in memory of Prof. A. S. Cook, 1934
      Manuscript reads: "Write an article on your damned Yankee bookstealing." Signed with initials.
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Fred. Kugelman to Professor Cook, 1919 June 8.
    - The Zodiac Song - Autograph manuscript in 12 verses., undated (Box 31)
- Artwork by Ruskin, 1846; Series III
  Series III, Artwork, has been left unarranged.
  - Water color drawings; pencil, pen and ink sketches. 14 pieces., 1833-1874, undated (Box 36 (Oversize))
    "Old Hall in Worcestershire" - Bought from Miss Elizabeth Norton on the Library Associates Fund, 1944.
    Other drawings and paintings - Gift of Charles E. Goodspeed, 1944 May
    The following are included:
    "The Rhone at Geneva." Watercolor, 25x17cm. "Sunset on Carrara Mountains, Spezia Bay." Watercolor, 26x18cm. 1874 April 7. "Chamouni, August 22." (On verso: "Vevay, August 25.") Watercolor, 18x13cm.
    "Old Hall in Worcestershire" (1854?). Wash and pencil sketch. 29x22cm on a mount 53x37cm.
    "Part of Geneva on the River." 1833. Pencil, pen, and ink sketch. 25x16cm (in a mount).
    "My first study of clouds". (Title in Mrs. Severn's hand). Pencil, pen, and ink sketch. 21x12cm. "Outlines of Aiguilles Ranges, Chamouni." 1846 or 1847 December 23. Signed. Drawing continued on verso. Pencil, pen, and ink sketch. 25x18cm. "Cleavages of Aiguille Bouchard." Pencil, pen, and ink sketch. 21x13cm. "Montagne de la Cote, summit from flank of Mont Blanc." Pencil sketch. 12x18cm. "The Aiguille Charmoz from window of the Union." 1849. Pencil sketch, with pen and ink sketch on verso. 12x9cm. "Valley of Cluses." Pencil, pen, and ink sketch. 18x11cm.
    2 unidentified sketches. 18x11cm and 17x1cm.
    Unidentified watercolor drawing, with pencil note in Ruskin's hand. 18x13cm.
  - "Evening in Arcadia" - Pen and ink sketch, undated (Box 32)
  - Albums of pencil sketches and water colors., undated (Box 32)
- Other Material, 1847-1874, undated; Series IV
  - Page of a printed preface, signed by Ruskin., undated (Box 33)
  - 3 portraits of Ruskin, undated (Box 33)
  - 8 plates of drawings by Ruskin., undated (Box 33)
  - Manuscript title page of Ulrich the Farm Servant., undated (Box 33)
    Accompanied by two portraits of Ruskin.
  - Photograph of John Ruskin, photograph of Ruskin's tomb., undated (Box 33)
  - Photograph of John Ruskin, signed., undated (Box 33)
  - Photographs (2) of John Ruskin., undated (Box 33)
  - Reproduction of a page of Ruskin's notebook., undated (Box 33)
    Used as the frontispiece for the Library Associates Report, 1936 June.
    Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Arnold Whitridge, 1936
  - Review of "Progression by Antagonism" by Lord Lindsay - Corrected galley proofs, with notes and corrections in manuscript, by J. G. Lockhart(?), with manuscript title page in an unidentified hand., 1847 (Box 33)
    Accompanied by proof pages of the article as it appeared in the Quarterly Review, Vol. LXXXI, no. CLXI.
    Accompanied by a strip of red cloth binding, lettered in gold: "Ruskin MS. Lord Lindsay's "Christian Art" Revise. 1847."
    Edges charred, affecting some manuscript notes.
  - Manuscript notebook of notes taken by Alexander H. M. Wedderburn at John Ruskin's lectures in Oxford. Bound in limp morocco., 1874 November-December; (1 volume) (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous material including photographs of paintings, watercolors by Ruskin and others (including William Collingwood), architectural sketches, etc. 13 items., undated (Box 37 (Oversize))
  - Miscellaneous photographs, engravings, etc., undated (Box 37 (Oversize))
  - Proofs of woodcuts by Arthur Burgess of drawings made by Ruskin for his works, and drawings and tracings made by pupils of the Ruskin drawing school at Oxford. 70 pieces., undated (Box 38 (Oversize))
    Includes 16 photographs of drawings by Ruskin.
    Gift of Warren H. Lowenhaupt, 1938
  - Ruskin's mailbag, undated (Box 39 (Oversize))
    Leather mailbag, engraved on the clasp: "Prof. Ruskin, Brantwood".